<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [ 
  <!ENTITY appversion "2.26">
  <!ENTITY app "gnome-user-share">
]>

<article id="index" lang="en">
  <articleinfo>
	 <title>Personal File Sharing Manual</title>
	 <copyright>
		<year>2009</year>
		<holder>Red Hat, Inc.</holder>
         </copyright>

	 <xi:include href="legal.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
	 <authorgroup>
           <author role="maintainer">
             <firstname>Matthias</firstname>
             <surname>Clasen</surname>
           </author>
	 </authorgroup>

<!-- According to GNU FDL, revision history is mandatory if you are -->
<!-- modifying/reusing someone else's document.  If not, you can omit it. -->
	 <revhistory>
		<revision>
		  <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
		  <date>2009</date>
		  <revdescription>
			 <para role="author">Matthias Clasen <email>mclasen@redhat.com</email></para>
		  </revdescription>
		</revision>
	 </revhistory>
	 <releaseinfo>This manual describes version &appversion; of &app;.</releaseinfo>
	 <legalnotice>
		<title>Feedback</title>
		<para>To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding the &app; application or this manual, follow the directions in the <ulink url="ghelp:user-guide?feedback-bugs" type="help">GNOME Feedback Page</ulink>.</para>
	 </legalnotice>
    <abstract role="description">
      <para>&app; is a session service that enables easy sharing of files
      between several computers.</para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>
  <indexterm><primary>gnome-user-share</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>file sharing</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>sharing</primary></indexterm>

  <sect1 id="gnome-user-share-intro">
	 <title>Introduction</title>
	 <para>
		&app; is a session service that exports the contents of the <filename>Public</filename> folder in your home directory, so that they can easily be accessed from other computers on the same local network. On the other computers, the shared folder will appear with a name like '<replaceable>user</replaceable>'s shared files' in the <application>nautilus</application> Network window, where <replaceable>user</replaceable> will be replaced by your user name.
	 </para>
	 <para>
		&app; uses a WebDAV server to share the <filename>Public</filename> folder, and advertises the share on the local network using mDNS.
	 </para>
         <para>
		Additionally, &app; can make the shared files available via ObexFTP over Bluetooth, and receive files that are sent to your computer via Bluetooth via ObexPush.
         </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="gnome-user-share-getting-started">
    <title>Getting started</title>

    <sect2 id="gnome-user-share-start">
       <title>Starting &app;</title>

       <para>
         The &app; service is normally started by <application>gnome-session</application> when you log in. You can change this by opening <menuchoice><guimenu>Preferences</guimenu><guimenu>Startup Applications</guimenu></menuchoice> in the <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu, and modifying the 'User Sharing' entry in the list of startup programs.
       </para>

       <para>
         To configure various aspects of file sharing, use the File Sharing Preferences, which can be found in the <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu under
         <menuchoice><guimenu>Preferences</guimenu><guimenu>Personal File Sharing</guimenu></menuchoice>.
       </para>
       <figure id="file-sharing-preferences">
         <title>File Sharing Preferences</title>
         <screenshot>
           <mediaobject>
             <imageobject>
               <imagedata fileref="figures/file-sharing-preferences.png" format="PNG"/>
             </imageobject>
           </mediaobject>
         </screenshot>
       </figure>
 
     </sect2>
     <sect2 id="gnome-user-share-enabling-sharing">
       <title>Enabling file sharing over the network</title>
       <para>
         Open the File Sharing Preferences using
         <menuchoice><guimenu>Preferences</guimenu><guimenu>Personal File Sharing</guimenu></menuchoice> in the <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu.  
       </para>
       <figure id="sharing-over-the-network">
         <title>Share Files over the Network</title>
         <screenshot>
           <mediaobject>
             <imageobject>
               <imagedata fileref="figures/sharing-over-the-network.png" format="PNG"/>
             </imageobject>
           </mediaobject>
         </screenshot>
       </figure>
       <para>
	       To enable file sharing via WebDAV, use the <guilabel>Share public files on network</guilabel> checkbox. When file sharing it enabled, the controls for password protection allow to set a password that needs to be specified before a user on another computer is granted access to the shared files. 
	 <note><para>Some firewall configurations on the local machine might cause problems with the advertisment, as well as the access to the shared files. Consult your system administrator for more details.</para></note>
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
              <para>
                Select <guilabel>Never</guilabel> to allow everybody to 
                freely read or write files in the shared folder.
              </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
              <para>
                Select <guilabel>Always</guilabel> to require the password 
                to read or write files in the shared folder.
              </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
              <para>
                Select <guilabel>When writing files</guilabel> to allow everybody
                to freely read files in the shared folder, but require the
                password when writing files.
              </para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
        <note><para>When you set a password, you have to give the password to all users that you want to have access to the shared files. Therefore, you should use a password that is different from other passwords you use.</para></note>
       </para>  
     </sect2>

     <sect2 id="gnome-user-share-enabling-bluetooth">
       <title>Enabling file sharing over Bluetooth</title>
       <para>
         Open the File Sharing Preferences using
         <menuchoice><guimenu>Preferences</guimenu><guimenu>Personal File Sharing</guimenu></menuchoice> in the <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu.  
       </para>
       <figure id="sharing-over-bluetooth">
         <title>Share Files over Bluetooth</title>
         <screenshot>
           <mediaobject>
             <imageobject>
               <imagedata fileref="figures/sharing-over-bluetooth.png" format="PNG"/>
             </imageobject>
           </mediaobject>
         </screenshot>
       </figure>
       <para>
         To enable file sharing via Bluetooth, use the <guilabel>Share public files over Bluetooth</guilabel> checkbox.
         To allow remote Bluetooth devices to delete files in your shared folder, use the <guilabel>Allow remote devices to delete files</guilabel> checkbox.
         To allow remote Bluetooth devices to access your shared files even when they are not bonded with your computer, use the <guilabel>Require remote devices to pair with this computer</guilabel> checkbox.
         <note><para>When you allow unbonded remote devices to access your shared files, anybody with a Bluetooth-enabled cell phone in the vicinity of your computer can access and perhaps even modify your shared files.
         </para></note>
       </para>
     </sect2>

     <sect2 id="gnome-user-share-bluetooth-receiving">
       <title>Receiving Files over Bluetooth</title>
       <para>
         Open the File Sharing Preferences using
         <menuchoice><guimenu>Preferences</guimenu><guimenu>Personal File Sharing</guimenu></menuchoice> in the <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu.  
       </para>
       <figure id="receiving-over-bluetooth">
         <title>Receive Files over Bluetooth</title>
         <screenshot>
           <mediaobject>
             <imageobject>
               <imagedata fileref="figures/receiving-over-bluetooth.png" format="PNG"/>
             </imageobject>
           </mediaobject>
         </screenshot>
       </figure>
       <para>
         To let remote Bluetooth devices send files to your computer, use the <guilabel>Receive files in Downloads folder over Bluetooth</guilabel> checkbox. Received files will be stored in the <filename>Downloads</filename> folder in your home directory. When receiving files is enabled, the <guilabel>Accept files</guilabel> selection allows you to determine which remote devices are allowed to send files.
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                 Select <guilabel>Always</guilabel> to allow any remote device to send files.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                  Select <guilabel>Only for Bonded devices</guilabel> to accept files only from bonded devices.
		  <note><para>Bonded devices are the ones that were connected to your computer, and had to enter a PIN code to connect to or from.</para></note>
                    
	      </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                  Select <guilabel>Only for Bonded and Trusted devices</guilabel> to accept files only from bonded devices.
		  <note><para>Devices can be marked as trusted in the <application>bluetooth-properties</application>'s <guilabel>Known devices</guilabel> section.</para></note>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
          Use the <guilabel>Notify about received files</guilabel> checkbox to select whether you want to be notified whenever a file is received via Bluetooth.
       </para>
     </sect2>
  </sect1>

</article>
